<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Positioning translational research in the biotech ecosystem: From basic research to more exploitable knowledge</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11428.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11428</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Novel scientific discoveries in the biomedical sector do not become viable clinical treatments or commercial products by themselves. There are numerous steps to go through and obstacles to overcome along the complex biomedical developmental process. Translational research has emerged to increase the speed of the conversion process and improve biomedical productivity. Since 2006, the National Institutes of Health (NIH)’s Clinical and Translational Science Awards (CTSA) program has supported over 60 institutions in order to improve the clinical and translational research environment. While current literature examines the effect of the NIH translational research program, the scope of its analysis is generally restricted to publication at the recipient level. This study analyzes the effect of the NIH CTSA program on biotech entrepreneurship by expanding the scope of analysis to a broader level. In addition, this project attempts to identify the effective combinations of conditions for a high level of biotech entrepreneurship with a specific emphasis on the role of translational research. The results will contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of the effect of translational research in the context of biotech entrepreneurial activity and help us to assess the potential benefit of translational research to the public health.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research draws on the entrepreneurial ecosystem approach and the knowledge spillover theory of entrepreneurship to analyze the effects of translational research on biotech entrepreneurship. The overarching analytical framework is that translational research increases biotech entrepreneurship by increasing the commercially exploitable knowledge stock that is available to entrepreneurs. For the empirical testing, the project uses federal innovation programs such as the Small Business Innovation Research as a proxy for biotech entrepreneurship. This study also considers and examines the biomedical patent, among other forms of exploitable knowledge. The empirical methods highlight how having the translational research program makes differences in the outcomes. Data is collected through various sources including federal agencies such as the National Institutes of Health, the National Science Foundation, and the Census Bureau. The findings will be principally disseminated through publication and will contribute to the literature in the translational research and entrepreneurial ecosystem fields. Additionally, federal agencies like the NIH will have access to a careful empirical appraisal of the CTSA program’s contribution to biomedical enterprises.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2022218</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Vonortas</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vonortas@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sang-Min</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sangminpark@gwmail.gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
