<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Resolution of Singularities, Valuation Theory and Related Topics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Spiroff</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The international mathematical conference ``Resolution of Singularities, Valuation Theory and Related Topics''  will be held from June 29 -  July 3, 2020 in Zacatecas, Mexico. The conference will be held at the Zacatecan Council of Science, Technology and Innovation. &lt;br/&gt;The conference will be devoted to recent progress in singularity theory and valuation theory. This meeting  will allow participants to establish new working relationships with leaders in this area, and to develop ongoing collaborations. NSF will provide travel and lodging support for 10 U.S. based participants to the conference. The emphasis on the funding will be towards students, postdoctoral scholars and young participants who do not have federal support. A particular emphasis will be on supporting a diversity of participants, especially from under-represented groups. The conference webpage is &lt;br/&gt;https://sites.google.com/view/spivakovsky60thbirthday/home?authuser=0.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference is focused on applications of Valuation Theory to Resolution of Singularities in positive characteristic  and to other areas of Algebraic Geometry, Commutative Algebra and Singularity Theory.  Besides local uniformization in positive and mixed characteristic, applications to local resolution of vector fields and the Pierce-Birkhoff conjecture will be given. Recently there have been significant advances in this area, and this conference will cover this progress in talks by the authors of this work.  The gathering will provide an opportunity for researchers from diverse fields to interact and establish research connections with each other; in particular, the  participants will benefit from this interaction and from seeing recent developments in the field and its relationships with other areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2002403</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Cutkosky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cutkoskys@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
