<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigation and Application of Pulse Shaping to High-Frequency Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR) / Zero-field Optically Detected Magnetic Resonance (ODMR) Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>475003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>475003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kelsey Cook</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemistry/Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging and Physics/Quantum Information Sciences programs, Professor Takahashi and his group at the University of Southern California are improving magnetic resonance spectroscopic techniques - important tools for characterizing the structure and motions/changes (dynamics) of chemical systems.  They are working to improve our understanding and control of the energy states of matter in order to enhance the sensitivity and level of detail with which chemical systems can be probed.  Professor Takahashi is also developing programs to train graduate and undergraduate students in the principles of quantum information science, magnetic resonance spectrometry, and nanotechnology.  The team enhances programs of science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) education for high school and elementary school students in the South Los Angeles community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Pulsed electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectroscopy can provide detailed information about molecular structure and dynamics. Like nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, pulsed EPR spectroscopy becomes more powerful at high magnetic fields and frequencies. The spectral resolution, spin polarization, sensitivity, and time resolution of pulsed EPR all increase with increasing magnetic field and the associated Larmor precession frequency. However, the measurement science of high field/frequency pulsed EPR has yet to be explored due to technological challenges. In this project, Professor Takahashi is utilizing a high-speed arbitrary waveform generator (AWG) for improvement of quantum control and investigation of the measurement science and applications of AWG-driven pulsed EPR at high fields and frequencies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2004252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susumu</FirstName>
<LastName>Takahashi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>susumuta@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7281</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
