<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Midwest Arithmetic Geometry and Number Theory Series</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Manes</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in a series of three weekend conferences in arithmetic geometry and number theory over three years (tentatively scheduled at the University of Illinois at Chicago, November 7-8, 2020; the University of Michigan, October 9-10, 2021; and the Ohio State University, October 22-23, 2022). This series, titled "Midwest Arithmetic Geometry and Number Theory Series (MAGNTS)" aims to bring together the researchers of the Midwest universities at various career stages. More information about the 2019 conference can be found at magnts.org.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each conference will have several components. Two mini-courses (approximately three hours each) by established researchers in number theory or arithmetic geometry will be followed by two research presentations (one hour each) by mid-career researchers in areas related to the mini-courses. The participants will get a chance to present their own research during a poster session, and there will be a career panel featuring people from various career paths, including academia, industry, and government positions. Through this setup, the conferences aim to expose the participants to cutting-edge research areas, as well as to provide an opportunity to explore various career options while networking with others of similar mathematical backgrounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2005736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roman</FirstName>
<LastName>Holowinsky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>holowinsky.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<EmailAddress>park.2720@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
