<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EoR-Spec: Revealing the reionization of the Universe with CII intensity mapping</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>961382.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>961382</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zoran Ninkov</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will map the formation and evolution of galaxies and the large-scale structure of the Universe.  The team will design, build and use an imaging spectrometer, which is referred to as EoR-Spec.  EoR-Spec will map the far-infrared spectral line of singly ionized carbon.  This carbon line traces where stars formed and allows mapping of the history of star formation over a large fraction of the universe?s existence.  Such mapping also reveals the underlying distribution of matter in the universe.  This instrument will utilize a new optimized telescope for this task located on an 18,400 foot mountain in northern Chile.  This program provides a training ground for both graduate and undergraduate students.  The PI and Co-I have trained, or are training, many PhDs and undergraduates including female and underrepresented minority researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program seeks to develop an instrument to study the evolution of star formation in galaxies from the Epoch of Reionization (EoR), when the first galaxies were forming to near ?Cosmic Noon?.  This is done by mapping the aggregate 158 micron [CII] line emission over large regions. Since the [CII] line tracks star formation, and star formation occurs at gravitational over-densities, this [CII] line intensity mapping traces the cosmic star formation rate.  It also illuminates the underlying and evolving Cosmic Web. To make such measurements, the team will build EoR-Spec.  This instrument will deploy on the 6 meter aperture Cerro Chajnantor Atcama Telescope (CCAT-prime), which is located at 5600m elevation in northern Chile and is expected to see first light in late 2021. The science is enabled by CCAT-prime and a combination of state-of-the-art technologies: broad-band Fabry?Pérot interferometer (FPI) etalons based on silicon substrate mirrors with metamaterial antireflection coatings and large format Kinetic Inductance Detector (KID) arrays.  The proposers have trained, or are training &gt;20 PhDs and &gt;80 undergraduates. About half of these are female and about 10 are underrepresented minority (URM) researchers. Students from local K-12 schools will visit team laboratories, and local K-12 schools will be visited by team scientists.  The team also plans Virtual Lab Visits and summer student workshops on instrumentation and science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2009767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
<LastName>Stacey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gjs12@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Niemack</LastName>
<EmailAddress>niemack@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
