<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Enhancement of Jackson State University Course-based Undergraduate Research Experience (JSU-CURE) Program in the Biological Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399958.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399958</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Emanuel WAddell</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at Jackson State University will take place in the Biology Department and course-based research will be used to increase student comprehension of foundational material. The project is expected to enhance the undergraduate STEM education for biology majors and better prepare them for the rigors and challenges of graduate school programs and STEM employment.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will enable Jackson State University to transform traditionally taught lectures and labs into courses that actively engage students in authentic scientific inquiry through inquiry-based instruction. Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CURES) will be utilized to enhance student research competency, improve the Biology curriculum, stimulate student interest in discovery and prepare students for entry into graduate school or the STEM workforce. The JSU-CURE program is expected to impact at least 500 undergraduate students. Implementation of the program will result in a significant increase of underrepresented minority students entering post-graduate education and careers in the STEM arena. The program will also establish a cohort of JSU-CURE scholars who will employ CURE knowledge to teach the next generation of STEM middle school and high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2011511</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Graham</LastName>
<EmailAddress>barbara.e.graham@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>timothy.turner@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gloria</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gloria.s.miller@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>LaDonnya</FirstName>
<LastName>Drummond</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ladonnya.s.drummond@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jacqueline.j.stevens@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Jackson State University</Name>
<CityName>Jackson</CityName>
<ZipCode>392170002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6019792008</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 J R LYNCH ST.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
