<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Infusion of Computer Technology into General and Organic Chemistry.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399948.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399948</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Emanuel WAddell</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP), through Targeted Infusion Projects, supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. This project at the University of Arkansas Pine Bluff (UAPB) will infuse the General and Organic Chemistry curriculum with web-based teaching tools and simulation software. It is expected that learning outcomes will be improved leading to an overall increase in retention.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to increase the number of students completing Organic Chemistry I and moving to Organic Chemistry II, resulting in an overall increase in retention of students in STEM disciplines. This project is also designed to incorporate Peer Led Team Learning (PLTL) practices into General and Organic Chemistry classes at UAPB. The intervention strategies will improve students? performance in organic chemistry leading to overall increase in retention of students in the sciences. It will also strengthen STEM curricula through infusion of new pedagogical approaches that will promote a greater depth of knowledge in Organic Chemistry. This project will quantify and analyze the effects of technology infusion in learning difficult concepts in Organic Chemistry. The study will also identify the effectiveness of educational TPACK Framework in framing the study for technology infusion in the classroom and laboratory settings. This project will help UAPB to produce a greater number of qualified minority graduates who will pursue careers in the STEM areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2011901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<EmailAddress>walker_r@uapb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Onyilagha</LastName>
<EmailAddress>onyilaghaj@uapb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grant</FirstName>
<LastName>Wangila</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wangilag@uapb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abul</FirstName>
<LastName>Kazi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kazia@uapb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff</Name>
<CityName>Pine Bluff</CityName>
<ZipCode>716012790</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8705758750</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
