<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Transmission Electron Microscope Digital Camera</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>139860.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>139860</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs as well as the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR). The University of South Dakota is acquiring a digital camera for a transmission electron microscope (TEM) to support Professor James Hoefelmeyer and colleagues Ranjit Koodali, Chaoyang Jiang, Grigoriy Sereda and Aravind Baride. In general, a TEM sends a beam of electrons through a thin layer of material. The electron beam interacts with the substance to produce a visual image, similar to a microscope. The images are recorded by a camera and they are important for research on the chemical properties of materials. The images reveal details of the structure, such as size and shape of a nanoparticle or a protein. This information helps researchers understand the material's properties and improve them. The acquisition enhances the training of undergraduates in research. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate and graduate students at this institution and nearby universities such as South Dakota State University, Nebraska Indian Community College (NICC, in South Sioux City, Macy and Santee, NE) and Red Cloud Indian School.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award significantly increases the capabilities and gives a new life to a heavily used transmission electron microscope. The award is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. It especially impacts studies controlling and characterizing plasmonic nanomaterials for surface enhanced Raman scattering and anti-counterfeiting applications. The instrumentation is also used for studying photocatalytic degradation of aqueous pollutants using nanoporous carbon materials and investigating lanthanide-doped NaYF4 (sodium ytrium tetrafluoride) upconversion nanocrystals for anti-counterfeiting applications. In addition, it provides information for exploring the use of solar fuels catalysis, fuel cells, and lithium ion batteries. The instrumentation is also used to identify antimicrobial coatings prepared by functionalized multilayered microparticles of graphene.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2018422</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ranjit</FirstName>
<LastName>Koodali</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ranjit.koodali@wku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoefelmeyer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>James.Hoefelmeyer@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chaoyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Jiang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>CY.Jiang@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grigoriy</FirstName>
<LastName>Sereda</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Grigoriy.Sereda@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aravind</FirstName>
<LastName>Baride</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aravind.baride@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Dakota Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>vermillion</CityName>
<ZipCode>570692307</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6056775370</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>414 E CLARK ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8604</Code>
<Text>Fuel Cells</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
