<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HACU National Internship Program NSF Summer Scholars</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>689681.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>226690</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sherrie Green</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Hispanic Association of Colleges and Universities (HACU) is the recipient of an award for summer internship support.  HACU, a national, non-profit organization, has a long and distinguished record of providing summer internship opportunities via the organization’s National Hispanic Internship Program (HNIP).  Through HNIP, academically prepared students throughout the US and Puerto Rico receive quality internship assignments through various federal government agencies. Participants are exposed to various career options in the Federal sector that serve to help students make informed decisions and solidify career objectives.  By partnering with the Federal government, HACU has successfully placed over 11,000 students in internships since HNIP commenced in 1992.  To continue its collaboration with HACU, the National Science Foundation, a participating government agency, will offer challenging assignments that will broaden the exposure of students pursuing careers in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM).  Internships create a unique opportunity for the Foundation to actively participate in strengthening the human capital infrastructure to achieve excellence in STEM education and developing a competitive STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>2022344</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reynaldo</FirstName>
<LastName>Decerega</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Reynaldo.Decerega@hacu.net</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hispanic Association of Colleges and Universities</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782299329</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2106923805</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8415 Datapoint Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>053Y</Code>
<Text>SSIP-Summer Scholars Internshi</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
